<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
    <title>David Edward Clark</title>
    <description>Focused on the intersection of writing, design, &amp; programming.</description>
    <language>en-ca</language>
    <link>http://www.davidedwardclark.com/</link>
    <item>
        <title>The Trouble with UX</title>
        <author>David Clark</author>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>User experience professional (UX) is a job title causing confusion in the web industry. A clear sign of it can be found in the coupling of the term UX with more standard job titles like designer and developer. This pairing occurs because UX by itself is too broad to describe what companies are looking for. However, by pairing UX with UI, developer, or analytics firms are simply diluting the meaning of the term even more.</p>
            <p>Just what does UX mean? The user experience is the whole experience. Absolutely everything. When you purchase an Apple product off their website and have it delivered, then use the product, the user experience in this case involves: your visit to the online store, taking the product out of the box, plugging it in, using the UI and doing things with it. It is everything. It isn&rsquo;t just your interaction with the user interface. Steve Jobs is the only one who could have claimed user experience as a job title at Apple, but even he didn&rsquo;t control every detail of the experience.</p>
            <p>Web applications and documents are not physical things like a laptop so the user experience in these cases is narrower. Thus people who call themselves user exerience professionals in companies who make stuff for the web are closer to what they say they are. Nonetheless the UX is still the whole experience. Just because Google search is only a website does not mean that the user experience is only its UI. One of the biggest things that effects the user experience is site performance. With Google search milliseconds can make a difference.</p>
            <p>But who makes Google search performant? Do they have a UX professional that makes this happen? After all it massively effects the user experience. No, developers make the site performant. It is their job and it is one of Google&rsquo;s mantra&rsquo;s to make their products as perfomant as possible. At Google developers not only create new key technologies but they also make them really fast. They control this key aspect of the user experience. Many other people have sway over aspects of the UX of Google&rsquo;s products. The company hires writers, designers, information artchitects and so on. Given the fact that in every case each person has an influencing factor on the user experience it wouldn&rsquo;t make sense to pretend that just one person controls the entire user experience now would it?</p>
            <p>And this is my problem with UX. No one person controls the user experience so why create job titles that would lead us to believe otherwise? Companies sub-consciously understand this so they end up tacking on qualifers to the UX position as mentioned earlier: UX/UI, UX Developer, UX/Analytics. This is because they know the person actually won&rsquo;t have control over the entire experience. My thinking is that they should simply state clearly what they are looking for to begin with withough using this UX prefix to begin with. It only causes confusion.</p>
            <p>I have an incling as to when this grevious error entered the lexicon of web professionals. It is the result of a <a href="http://vimeo.com/4304573">talk given by Jesse James Garett (JJG)</a> in 2009 at the 10<sup>th</sup> Annual IA Summit. Mr. Garett is a smart chap but I think he jumps the gun in his talk when he states that IA&rsquo;s have always been user experience professionals. It is as if he wants IA&rsquo;s to switch their job titles so they can commandeer the industry like pirates: &ldquo;we are user experience professionals thus you must listen to us and obey our mandates!&rdquo; It is as if JJG didn&rsquo;t think IA&rsquo;s were getting the respect they deserved in the industry so by changing their titles he thought it would give them what they need.</p>
            <p>Unfortunately all it has done is cause confusion. The work still needs to be done we are just less clear on who is doing it. The following is a list of job titles which I think the industry ought to stick to:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>Analytics</li>
                <li>Information Architect</li>
                <li>Content Strategist</li>
                <li>UI Designer</li>
                <li>Front End Developer</li>
                <li>Application Developer</li>
                <li>Database Developer</li>
            </ul>
            <p>There is room in our industry for more job titles but lets make sure we introduce titles that provide clarity. A job title like user experience professional simply causes confusion.</p>
        ]]></description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 1 Jun 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.davidedwardclark.com/the-trouble-with-ux.html</link>
        <guid>http://www.davidedwardclark.com/the-trouble-with-ux.html</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title>Where I&rsquo;ve Been</title>
        <author>David Clark</author>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>A high school math teacher introduced me to the golden ratio. The idea that there is a relationship between numbers and beauty fascinated me and still does to this day. Studying the golden ratio drew my attention to the renaissance artists. The intersection of math, geometry and art was intriguing but I ended up applying my interest to the art &amp; science of user interface design. Around this time I was studying database administration. The dual strands of information management and interface design intertwined to set my career trajectory early on. I haven&rsquo;t been able to shake my interest in either.</p>
            <p>Soon after college I had my first job. It was 2003. That first year I hacked around in dreamweaver switching between the design and code views. I had a bit of experience with HTML, CSS &amp; PHP from the previous year working on a small project with former college mates but I hadn&rsquo;t paid much attention to what I was doing. Now I had a full time job and needed to know. That summer I read Jakob Nielson&rsquo;s Designing Web Usability and shortly after Jeffrey Zeldman&rsquo;s Designing with Web Standards. They had a lasting impact. Those books taught me that there are better and worse ways of doing things. While Nielson &amp; Zeldman were early influences shortly after Dan Cederholm and Jeremy Keith played an important role in my development. I became fond of the web and the community that sustains it.</p>
            <p>In the years between then and now I worked at different companies and tried my hand at different aspects of the craft. I didn&rsquo;t always take seriously my new found passion. Spare time was often filled with activities not nourishing of my chosen field. Something changed recently. I want to be really good at what I do now.</p>
            <p>Along with a newfound commitment to my practice comes a willingness to long form writing. Exercising the writing muscle improves thinking &amp; process, and provides a space for self reflection. Side projects now dominate my spare time. A few friends and I have created javascript &amp; typography study groups. These organised learning sessions have been an immense joy and I recommend them to anyone who wants to hone their skill. I look forward to contributing my thoughts to a community which has given me so much.</p>
        ]]></description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.davidedwardclark.com/where-ive-been.html</link>
        <guid>http://www.davidedwardclark.com/where-ive-been.html</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title>Beautiful Instruments</title>
        <author>David Clark</author>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Before me sits a 13" MacBook Air paired with iA Writer in focus mode. The two together create a serene environment in which thought easily passes from mind to machine. Tools subtly effect what we create. Get the best and only what you need. This is my setup.</p>
            <h2>13" MacBook Air</h2>
            <ul>
                <li>Google Chrome for browsing and developing.</li>
                <li>Terminal for command line UNIX.</li>
                <li>iA Writer for writing.</li>
                <li>Adobe Photoshop &amp; Illustrator for design.</li>
                <li>TextMate for writing code.</li>
                <li>Panic Transmit for FTP&rsquo;ing &amp; S3 access.</li>
                <li>Firefox &amp; Safari for browser testing.</li>
                <li>Parallels with Windows 7 for gaming and IE testing.</li>
                <li>SuperDuper! for hard drive backups.</li>
                <li>Colloquy for IRC.</li>
            </ul>
            <h2>iPhone 4s</h2>
            <ul>
                <li>Web versions of Gmail, Google Reader &amp; Tasks.</li>
                <li>iA Writer for edits.</li>
                <li>Tweetbot for Twitter.</li>
                <li>Instapaper for reading saved articles.</li>
            </ul>
            <h2>Retina iPad</h2>
            <ul>
                <li>Paper with a Cosmonaut Stylus for drawing.</li>
                <li>FontBook for browsing type specimens.</li>
                <li>Comic Zeal for reading back issues of Heavy Metal.</li>
                <li>Web versions of Gmail &amp; Google Reader.</li>
                <li>iA Writer for writing and edits.</li>
                <li>Tweetbot for twitter.</li>
                <li>Instapaper for reading saved articles.</li>
            </ul>
            <h2>Accessories</h2>
            <ul>
                <li>Apple In-Ear Headphones.</li>
                <li>Logitech Anywhere MX mouse.</li>
                <li>WD My Passport Studio external hard drive.</li>
                <li>iPhone 3GS for testing.</li>
            </ul>
            <h2>Backups</h2>
            <ul>
                <li>Dropbox for commonly used files.</li>
                <li>Bi-monthly backup of MacBook HD to My Passport Studio.</li>
                <li>Crashplan for backing up My Passport Studio to cloud.</li>
            </ul>
            <h2>Hosting</h2>
            <ul>
                <li>Flickr for photos.</li>
                <li>Github for projects with code.</li>
                <li>TypeKit for fonts.</li>
                <li>Linode for websites.</li>
                <li>Namecheap for domains.</li>
                <li>Amazon S3 for website backups.</li>
            </ul>
        ]]></description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 15 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.davidedwardclark.com/beautiful-instruments.html</link>
        <guid>http://www.davidedwardclark.com/beautiful-instruments.html</guid>
    </item>
</channel>
</rss>